A Guide to the Records of the Office of Equal Opportunity/Affirmative Action, 1986-2006
Special Collections, Virginia Tech
Special Collections, Virginia Tech
Records of the Office of Equal Opportunity/Affirmative Action, 1986-2006
Special Collections, Virginia Tech, Blacksburg, Va.
RG 6/4/5
1.65 Cubic Feet; 2 boxes
The collection contains materials from Michele Holmes relating to Equal Opportunity and Affirmative Action (EO/AA) at Virginia Tech from 1986 through 2006. It includes EO/AA minutes, affirmative action plans, proposals, grants, executive orders, and information on faculty recruitment, the Family Friendly Policy Task Force, and awards. It also contains materials relating to various events, including Black Alumni Reunions, and areas of concern as well as information regarding the work force and lists of black alumni.
Virginia Polytechnic Institute and State University. Office for Equal Opportunity
Holmes, Michele
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
Collection is open for research.
Acquisition Information
The Records of the Office of Equal Opportunity/Affirmative Action were donated to Special Collections in multiple accruals, from 2002 through 2006.
Administrative History
The Equal Employment/Affirmative Action Advisory Committee was formed in Fall 1975. It disbanded in 2003 with formation of the Commission on Equal Opportunity and Diversity.
The Office for Equal Opportunity and the Office of Multicultural Affairs combined in 2008 to form the Office for Equity and Inclusion. The equal opportunity function was restructured to fall under Human Resources in Spring 2010. When that broke off, the Office for Equity and Inclusion became the Office for Diversity and Inclusion, and the Office of Equal Opportunity became Equity and Access under Human Resources.
Materials in this collection were collected by Michele Holmes who started work in the Equal Opportunity/Affirmative Action office in the 1979-80 session and later co-edited Minority News.
Scope and Content
The collection contains materials from Michele Holmes relating to Equal Opportunity and Affirmative Action (EO/AA) at Virginia Tech from 1986 through 2006. It includes EO/AA minutes, affirmative action plans, proposals, grants, executive orders, and information on faculty recruitment, the Family Friendly Policy Task Force, and awards. It also contains materials relating to various events, including Black Alumni Reunions, and areas of concern as well as information regarding the work force and lists of black alumni.
Arrangement
The colleciton is arranged alphabetically.
Adjunct Descriptive Data
Separated Materials
Faculty/staff photographs have been removed and added to the Faculty/Staff Photograph Collection. Photocopies of the images removed remain in this collection.
Index Terms
Subjects:
Affirmative action programs; Educational equalization; University History; University Archives
Organizations:
Virginia Polytechnic Institute and State University; Virginia Polytechnic Institute and State University. Office for Equal Opportunity
Contents List
- Affirmative Action Award, 1994-1996 (Box 1, Folder 1)
- Affirmative Action Incentive Grants Program, 1990-1991, 1993, 1995, 1997 (Box 1, Folder 2)
- Affirmative Action Plan, 1997 (Box 1, Folder 3)
- Affirmative Action Requirements Relating to Publications, 1985, 1992-1994 (Box 1, Folder 4)
- African American House Proposal, 1990 (Box 1, Folder 5)
- Black Alumni Reunion, 1986-2000 (Box 1, Folder 6)
- Black Athletes - Football, 1998, 2001 (Box 1, Folder 7)
- Black Faculty and Staff, 1986-1987 (Box 1, Folder 8)
- "Breakfast with..." Speakers Series, 1990-1994 (Box 1, Folder 9)
- Campus Locator - Black Faculty and Staff (2 folders), 1987-2002 (Box 1, Folder 10-11)
- Chideya, Farai, 1999 (Box 1, Folder 12)
- Classroom and Campus Climate, Committee on, 1991, 1993 (Box 1, Folder 13)
- Conference for Potential Graduate Students, 1989, 1991 (Box 1, Folder 14)
- Coordinating Council for Women's Concerns, 1998-2001 (Box 1, Folder 15)
- Elliot, Jane, 1994 (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - "Examining Issues of Racism and Discrimination"
- Employee Relations, 1989 (Box 1, Folder 17)
- Equal Opportunity - US Government Print, 1992 (Box 1, Folder 18)
- Equal Opportunity/Affirmative Action Committee - Minutes, 1987-1988 (Box 1, Folder 19)
- Equal Opportunity/Affirmative Action Committee - Minutes, 1988-1989 (Box 1, Folder 20)
- Equal Opportunity/Affirmative Action Committee - Minutes, 1989-1990 (Box 1, Folder 21)
- Equal Opportunity/Affirmative Action Committee - Minutes, 1990-1991 (Box 1, Folder 22)
- Equal Opportunity/Affirmative Action Office - Voluntary Reporting of Veteran Status, 1988 (Box 1, Folder 23)
- Equal Opportunity/Affirmative Action Office - Quarterly Report, 1999 (Box 1, Folder 24)
- Ethnic Minority Enrollment Report, 1987 (Box 1, Folder 25)
- Executive Order on Equal Opportunity, 1994 (Box 1, Folder 26)
- Faculty Recruitment, 1980-1982, 1993, 1995 (Box 1, Folder 27)
- Family-Friendly Policy Task Force (2 folders), 1990-1991, 1994-1997 (Box 1, Folder 28-29)
- Final Child Care Report by the Committee on Equal Opportunity/Affirmative Action, 1988 (Box 1, Folder 30)
- Gospel Experience Reunion, 1996 (Box 1, Folder 31)
- Guinier, Lani - "Why We Need a National Conversation on Race", 1995 (Box 1, Folder 32)
- Herndon, Michael - Board of Visitors Representative, 1998 (Box 1, Folder 33)
- History of Black Sororities and Fraternities, 1987 (Box 1, Folder 34)
- Hooks, Bell, 1996 (Box 1, Folder 35)
- Hunt, Thomas C. - "Hampton Institute and its Founder, the Early Years" (Box 1, Folder 36)
- Listing of Black Alumni (2 folders), 1989 (Box 1, Folder 37-38)
- Listing of Black Alumni by Alphabet, 1991 (Box 1, Folder 39)
- Listing of Black Alumni by Alphabet, 1996 (Box 1, Folder 40)
- Listing of Black Alumni by Alphabet, 1998 (Box 1, Folder 41)
- Listing of Black Alumni by Alphabet (2 folders), 2000 (Box 1, Folder 42-43)
- Listing of Black Alumni by Class Year, 1954-1999 (Box 1, Folder 44)
- Listing of Black Alumni by Class Year, 1996 (Box 1, Folder 45)
- Listing of Black Alumni by Class Year, 1998 (Box 1, Folder 46)
- Listing of Black Alumni by State, 1998 (Box 1, Folder 47)
- Listing of Black Alumni by State, 2000 (Box 1, Folder 48)
- Listing of Black Alumni by Zip Code, 1986 (Box 1, Folder 49)
- Listing of Black Alumni by Zip Code, 1996 (Box 1, Folder 50)
- Mfume, Kwesi, 1998 (Box 1, Folder 51)
- Minority Newsletter, 1992-1993 (Box 1, Folder 52)
- New Conflict Resolution Program, 2006 (Box 1, Folder 53)
- Office of Federal Contract Compliance Programs - Technical Assistance Program, 1991 (Box 1, Folder 54)
- Overton R. Johnson Endowed Scholarship Step Competition, 1989 (Box 1, Folder 55)
- Phallisha Newsome, Truman Scholar, 1992 (Box 1, Folder 56)
- Photographs of Black Faculty and Staff, 1986, 1991 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  Separated Materials
  Photographs of black faculty and staff have been removed to the faculty/staff alphabetical files of the University Photograph Collection. Collection contains only photocopies.
- Profiles in Excellence - Black Student Life at Virginia Tech, 1988-1989 (Box 2, Folder 2)
- Program of Graduate Assistance for Minority Virginians, 1986-1987 (Box 2, Folder 3)
- Report for the Committee on Recruitment, Enrollment and Retention, 1995 (Box 2, Folder 4)
- Search and Screening Committees, 1991 (Box 2, Folder 5)
- Sexual Harrassment Policy, 1983-1984 (Box 2, Folder 6)
- Smith House, 1989 (Box 2, Folder 7)
- Special Services for Disabled Students, 1983, 1985, 1993, 2000 (Box 2, Folder 8)
- Spectrum Supplement, 1996-02-22 (Box 2, Folder 8A)
- Steinem, Gloria, 1996 (Box 2, Folder 9)
- Takaki, Ronald, 1995 (Box 2, Folder 10)
- Wise, Tim - "Who Will Speak on Affirmative Action?", 1999 (Box 2, Folder 11)
- Work Force Analysis for Full-Time Faculty, 1994 (Box 2, Folder 12)
- Work Force Profile Data, 1987 (Box 2, Folder 13)
- The University Plan, 1990 (Box 2, Folder 14)